The Horseless Carriage, a collection of automobile history, 1893-1965 bulk 1938-1955
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
The Horseless Carriage Collection of Automobile History 1893-1965 (bulk 1938-1955)
MS 035
Smith, Steadman. Collector
The Horseless Carriage Collection of Automobile History consist of pamphlets, magazines, promotional reports, newspaper articles, advertisements, calendars, newsletters, photographs, and other pictorial items relating to the history and development of the automobile, dated 1893 to 1965. Most are items distributed by car-related businesses in the 1940s and 1950s. Earlier materials are nostalgic reprints of turn-of-the-century materials.
.9 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
An attorney and a car enthusiast from Southern California; Steadman Smith was active in antique automobile clubs and gathered these materials related to his interests.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Series I: Automobile history, 1893-1965 bulk 1938-1955
Scope and Content Note
Collection of printed materials and photographs relating to cars, from their early development in the 1890s through the contemporary trends of the 1960s including pamphlets, magazines, promotional reports, newspaper articles, advertisements, calendars, newsletters, pictorial items and photographs. The turn-of-the-century items are nostalgic reprints; the earliest original item is a 1924 Automobile Trade Journal. Most of the items date from the 1940s and 1950s, and were distributed by car and tire dealerships, auto manufacturers, petroleum and motor oil corporations, automobile clubs, and the specialty publisher Floyd Clymer.
There are newsletters, clippings and notices of activities, mostly from 1938 to 1949, for the Horseless Carriage Club. Some publicity brochures describe particular makes of cars. Most of the material relates to the United States but a small amount is about the British and German automobile industries. Brochures and clippings commemorate special events such as the 1908 New York to Paris race, J. Frank Duryea’s winning of America’s first automobile race in 1895 and its fiftieth anniversary in 1945, and the automobile industry’s celebration of its Golden Jubilee in 1946. Black-and-white photographs are present, 1938 to 1940, of collectors with their antique cars, and there are several original drawings by Alexander G. Telatco. Calendars from 1946 and 1953 have color reprints of early cars in Americana settings by artists such as Norman Rockwell.
A longer and more complete run of Horseless Carriage Club Gazette is cataloged in the Library’s main collection
Access Terms
Duryea, J. Frank (James Frank), 1869-1967
Horseless Carriage Club
Antique and classic cars
Automobile rallies—History
Automobile industry and trade—History
Automobiles—Societies, etc.
Automobiles—Pictorial works
Automobiles—Collectors and collecting—United States
Automobiles—Social aspects—History
Automobiles—Design and construction—History
Smith, Steadman, collector
Container List
- Automobile history materials, 1893-1965; bulk 1938-1955
  This series is arranged by type of material.
  - Historical articles (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Historical photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Automobile Trade Journal, (historical issue), December 1, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Advertisements (magazine) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Floyd Clymer’s “Independent Test Report and Investigation of [various] cars”, 1940's (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mobilgas Economy Run, (Grand Canyon), 1950; 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Frank Duryea and America’s First Automobile Race (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Horseless Carriage Club, Los Angeles (Misc. materials) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Horseless Carriage Club Gazette, v.1-9, 1938-1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Antique Automobile Club of America (Misc. materials) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pictorial items and cartoons (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tours, races and club activities (various) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Automobile Industry Golden Anniversary, commemorative publicatons, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous items, The Times (London), Survey of the British Motor-Car Industry, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Brochures about various automobiles (Box 3)
  - Two pictorial calendars (Box 3)
  - 1st Annual Revival, Glidden tour, (reprint of newspaper publicity), 1946 (Box 3)